Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 3 -- Letters to Franklin 1778 April-December Mss.B.F85inventory03
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, G. London
    Captain Barnard has shown much kindness to unfortunate Americans; asks Franklin to grant him any favor in his power.
    A. E. by Franklin. Praising Mr. Williams, a surgeon, for his kindness to the American prisoners.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 October 3; A.L.S. 3p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Concerning the sale of a vessel belonging to Mr. Ross, whose agent refuses to pay the seamen, who shipped on her, their due wages; refers the matter to the Commissioners. Sends them two hogsheads of wine of Medoc.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 October 3; L.S. 3p.; Thomas Grant and Joses Hill. Bordeaux
    Crew of the vessel Nancy, of Edenton, North Carolina, at Bordeaux, petition them to adjust their claims with the French Admiralty.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Maire de Gimel, Jacques. Nantes
    M. Gruel's vessel the safest means of sending the various articels to Virginia. As [Arthur] Lee refuses to advance him another sou begs Franklin to let him have the necessary sum.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 3; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Rolandeau, -----. Paris
    Asks if there is a letter for him in Franklin's keeping; desires certificete of his service in the American army, of his imprisonment and subsequent arrival in England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 4; A.L.S. 3p.; Hartley, David
    Proposition concerning a treaty of peace.
    Partly printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 301, Note; Bigelow, VI, 219, Note).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Sr
    Introducing Mr. Henry Bromfield, of Boston.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Hartley, David
    Peace and friendship between the two nations still practicable; his plan for getting over the chief stumbling block.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Herault, Mrs Robert. Calais
    Begging for news of the cutter Benjamin, commanded by Captain Pierre Ricot, which sailed for the United States a year before; her husband was second in command and she is in the deepest anxiety about his fate.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Prevented from coming over to Paris by his undertaking a work on the subject of smallpox and inoculation. Promises to show him certain experiment he has made with inflammable air. Hears that Dr. Mesmer is in Paris and has been presented to the Royal Academy, also that his stuff about magnetical effluvia, too insipid to gain the ear of an old woman, is believed in by M. Le Roy, who protects him and will recommend him in London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Marcenay, Madame Herbaut de
    On what day would Franklin do her sister and herself the honor of dining with them; as not until he has honored them by his presence can they enjoy the pleasure of dining with him at passy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Morand, Dr Jean François Clèment. Paris
    Desires to use an illustration of the Franklin stove in his book and begs Franklin to write a brief explanation if it to accompany the engraving.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Moreau, ------. Versailles
    Sending Franklin two letters delivered for him to the porter of the cornte de Vergennes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 6; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thompson, Sec[retar]y. 1p.; The Continental Congress
    Directing the American Commissioners to inform Dr. Price that it is the desire of Congress to consider him as a citizen and to receive his assistance in regulating thier finances.
    Printed in the Secret Journals of Congress, Boston, 1820. II. 101.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 October 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    The arrival of a small cutter from Baltimore; no word of Comte d' Estaing's operations. News of other vessels.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Amiel, Charlotte. Auteuil
    Begging to know what prospect there is of Mr. Amiel's succeeding at Brest, and praying him to push the matter on; hopes the disappointment he experienced at Dunkirk will not be repeated.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Galbert, Gaspard, vicomte de. Brest
    Concerning sugar belonging to him on board the Isabella, which was captured by a Guernsey corsair and delivered by an American frigate.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 7; L.S. 6p.; Grinnell, Richard. Passy
    With reference to the English whaling vessels manned by Americans sailing from London and protected by the British fleets.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 7; L.S. 2p.; Harrison, Robert. Dinan
    An American seaman, taken prisoner on an English privateer, asks to be sent home.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Emery, John. Bilbao
    Arrival of the schooner. Lively, Captain Dupuy, from Newburyport, with the enclosed papers; therein Franklin will see the dispositions made to attack Rhode Island, and their probable failure owing to Comte d'Estaing's conduct in refusing to wait twenty-four hours and assist General Sullivan.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Tournelle, — de (consul). La Corogne
    Enclosing a packet for the Canary Islands.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 3; L.S. 4p.; Luet de Biscontin, —. Venice
    In case America establishes consulships in foreign countries, offers himself for the position at Venice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 3; A.L.S. 4p.; Cotière, Cathallet. St. Sulpice de la Pointe
    Desires information concerning the remedy of tobacco ashes in cases of dropsy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Merlet, -----. Paris
    Enclosing a copy of a letter (1 p.) received from his two nephews, M. de La Neuville, general of division under General Gates, and his brother, aide-de-camp to General Conway; begs Franklin to forward the enclosed letters to them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 8; A.L.S. 3p.; Cadet, -----. Paris
    Sends him some bread made out of potatoes; a discovery by himself and his friend, M. Parmentier; its advantages as compared with flour bread.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 October 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Collas, Peter. Passy
    Having bought certain articles in France, he was carrying them to America when he was captured by a Guernsey frigate and after making his way back to Calais, his trunk was searched and his possessions taken from him as English manufacture; begs them to help him recover these articles.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Keating, William. Dinnant Castle
    Is a native of Virginia to which country he is desirous of returning; the various vicissitudes he has encountered; begs Franklin to obtain his release from prison and a passage on board some American vessel.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 8; A.L. 7p.; Henemer, Abbé Jacob. Mannheim
    The Palatinate Academy of Sciences, wishing to show its admiration for Franklin, desires to present him with five books, dealing with history and philosophy; the fourth volume contains four papers by himself on electricity. Regrets his ignorance of English and Franklin's lack of acquaintance with German. Suggestions for rendering the works of the various Societies more widely known. Urges the desirability of establishing a German Society in Philadelphia; encloses a catalogue of the books necessary to carry out such a project.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 8; A.L.S. 3p.; Douglass, Andrew. Senlis jail
    His misfortunes since he sailed from Boston in April; his miserable situation in a French prison; begs Franklin to obtain his release and promises to serve America in any capacity he may suggest.
  - to The American Commissioners., [1778.] October 9; A.L.S. 4p.; Barnard, Tristram
    Absent from America four years; employed in the English service; desires to return home and share his country's fate; asks for papers which will protect him against American vessels. Full account of a most valuable whale-fishery discovered by England since the present contest opened; details the movements of the ships employed therein.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Hartley, David
    Quotes the answer from the Admiralty Office to his letters concerning an exchange of prisoners; their refusal to make any exchange except man for man.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 9; A.L.S. 3p.; Berny, Chevalier de
    Has received no answer to the five or six letters he has written Franklin, though it is a year since he sent him a pamphlet entitled "L'Œ du Maitre." The King, Queen and other sovereigns have honored his with kind acknowledgments; claims a similar courtesy from Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Buffot de Millery, — de. Santenay
    Franklin's promise to obtain news from America of M. le Vicomte de Mauroy, whose affairs were left in his hands.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 October 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Izard, Ralph. Paris
    Indignant at M. de Sartine's letter of the 7th inst., in which he is reffered to a course of law for the recovery of his baggage on board the ship Nile, carried into Marscilles by a French privateer; founds his claim upon an article in the treaty; begs that they will speak of it to M. de Sartine.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Bailly, —, aîné. Nantes
    Concerning a bill of exchange drawn by Mr. Bingham on Messrs. Franklin and Adams.
  - to The American Commissioner., 1778 October 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Applying for a letter of marque for Mr. Livingston's new ship, named after that respectable family. The case of Louis Lizete, a citizen of Quebec who desires to become a subject of France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Lesguillon, -----
    Writes on behalf of one of his old domestics, who left his service to enter that of Captain Jameson, an American, who has paid him no wages.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Maire de Gimel, Jacques. Nantes
    Implores Franklin, once again, to advance him sufficient money to fulfil his orders from the Government of Virginia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 10; A.L.S. 4p.; Niehaus. Alexander. Haselünne in Münster
    Wishes to supply the American army with Osnabrück linen and with stockings.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 10; A.L.S. 2p.; de la Prade, Chevalier. Souillac
    Desires to serve in the army of the United States; his former military experience; offers to raise a troop of deserters, a course which has before proved very successful.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 10; A.L.S. 5p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning a dispute between Mr. Schweighauser and himself relative to the ship Drake; explains the affair in detail.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 10; A.L.S. 5p.; Rieger, Jacob. Heidelberg
    Begging Franklin to enclose certain letters in his next packet to America. While travelling in Germany, has worn his uniform of an American officer and, from the lord to the peasant, has found only friends to the cause. Discontent among the Protestants in Germany owing to their rulers being chiefly Catholics. Opinions expressed as to the present war between the Emperor and King of Prussia.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 October 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Moylan, James. L'Orient
    Difficulty in disposing of Captain McNeill's prisoners. Concerning proposals received from the original proprietors of the French Reprisal, to allow Captain McNeill a third thereof for his protection.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Stettenhoven, — de. Geneva
    Has a great desire to serve America and believes he can be useful either through his talents or his bravery; his former military experience.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 12; A.L.S. 3p.; Pattulls, -----. St. Germain-en-Laye
    Laying before Franklin certain plans for the future welfare of America, after her independence is assured.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 October 12; A.L.S. 2p.; McNeill, Daniel. L'Orient
    Desires to know what is to be done with his prisoners; wishes their opinion on the law-suit in regard to the lsabella, whose former proprietors are doing all in their power to delay the course of justice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 12; A.L.S. 3p.; Douglass, Andrew. Saint Denis
    Setting forth the same grievances as those in his letter of the 8th inst., only with more detail, and begging to be put un board some American privateer.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 October 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Lovell, James. Philadelphia
    Sending the last prints of Dunlap with the Boston papers; will not pretend to unravel the designs of the enemy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October [12?]; A.L.S. 3p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Concerning a certain passage in the Declaration made by the Burgomasters of Amsterdam. Makes some excuses for the attitude of the Grand Pensionnaire. His intention to present Mr. Austin to the French Ambassador.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 12; L.; John Lemon, Edward Driver and John Nichols. Dinan
    Begging Franklin to obtain their release from prison.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 13; A.L.S. 3p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Number of prizes taken. An engagement between a Spainard and an English privateer which has occasioned the sending out of two Spanish frigates in pursuit. Offers to send a load of woolens and such seasonable articles to the states without delay.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Valltravers, Rodolph. Bienne
    Having received no answer to his last four letters will cease troubling Franklin. His regret at the failure of his plans for the union of Switzerland and the United States. The enclosed letter on behalf of Colonel Minning he hopes will be graciously received by Franklin and President Laurens.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 15; Poissonnier, Pierre. Paris
    Commissioned by the Royal Society of Medicine to renew Franklin's invitation to attend their public meeting on the 20th of that month.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Hard treatment meted out to Captain Lemaire, the officer appointed by Virginia for the inspection of military stores.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778 October 15]; A.L. 2p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Note on a letter by Franklin to the Court of Spain. Thinks it should be more specific, and he might add that he is going to lay the complaint before Congress with a view of obtaining satisfaction for Captain Conyngham's misconduct.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 16; A.L.S. 3p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Wishes to know the truth of the report that Rhode Island is taken and vessels of Byron's flect captured. Promises him a great reception when he shall visit Holland as the United states Minister; time not yet ripe.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 Dec. 16; A.L.S. 3p.; de Razetti, Baron. Paris
    Desires to serve in the American army; his military experience; at present, owing to debts, is hiding in Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Buchoz, ------. Paris
    Enclosing two catalogues of his library, which he is willing to sell on advantageous terms.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Introducing M. Huet Du Plessis.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 18; L.S. 2p.; Robert Harrison and John Lemon. Dinan
    Two American prisoners taken into British vessels petition for their release and for means to return to the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Patriot, A Sincere. Joshua Steele. London
    Dares not put his name to a mere philosophic letter while his country is under the sway of ignorance and malevolence. Sending him a publication of the Society of Arts and a pamphlet, just out, entitled The West India Merchant. The injuries done to those defenceless islands by American privateers have failed in their purpose of wounding England; the desire of many planters, if not for peace, for neutrality; plead the Islanders' cause.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Mané, -----. Paris
    Has made a medallion of Franklin, in ivory, for the Royal Academy of Sciences, and takes great pleasure in sending a duplicate to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 19; L. 2p.; -----, -----
    A wealthy person residing at Liège makes an offer to Franklin to supply the free states of America with all kinds of arms, at a much lower price than they are now paying and payment to be made only on delivery. Reply to this offer to be sent to M. Montecot, attorney in Parliament at Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 19; A.L.S. 3p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. Brest
    Is disgraced in the eyes of Brest and the French fleet; his indignation against M. de Sartine who has done him such dishonor. Concerning his letter to the King and the best means of delivering it. His filial veneration for Franklin and his earnest desire to hear from him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 19; L.S.; Girardot, Haller and Co. Paris
    Recommending to Franklin's protection, Mr. Foache, bookseller of Neufchatel.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 20; A.L.S. 4p.; Penn, Richard. London
    Through his marriage to Franklin's late ward, Miss Masters, as well as by inheritance, he owns great property in Pennsylvania and New Jersey, yet for more than two years has been unable to procure a shilling from that country; probably by this time, his agent, Mr. Tench Francis, has a considerable sum in hand for him; desires Franklin to point out the best way for him to procure a temporary subsistence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Cadet-le-jeune, M
    The Lieutenant-General of Police accepts the appointment made for their meeting at the Hotel Royal des Invalides. Will discuss the question of bread made from potatoes and bread-making in general. M. Parmentier, the celebrated chemist, will present a work of his to Franklin on the subject.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 October 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Livingston, Abraham. Charleston
    Explaining why his hopes of sending remittances to France on the public account have been frustrated.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Marolles de Lucé, Alexandre-Louis, chevalier de. Paris
    Describes his cruel situation; his wife ill, and he himself suffering intensely from a wound in his thigh, without proper food, medicines or money; begs for two or three Louis d'or to help him regain his health; M. Elié de Beaumont has spoken to Franklin in his favor.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, Jacques. Paris
    Begging for a letter of recommendation on behalf of a friend's nephew, who is about to sail for Charleston.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 October 21; L.S. 1p.; Keating, William et al. Dinan
    Ten American prisoners confined in Dinan Castel renew thier appeal to be released and employed in the service of the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 21; A.L.S. 3p. 6p.; Deane, Silas. Philadelphia
    Enclosing a translation of certain letters and despatches of Mr. Izard which, through written to a private friend, were introduced into Congress, read and filed; was too modest to follow literally some of the most abusive parts. The enemy about to make an expedition of some consequence. Mr. Lee's estimate of a suitable salary for himself and Mr. Adams.
    Enclosure. A translation of the letters of Ralph Izard to Henry Laurens. Giving an account of his situation, expressing his hatred of Franklin and Deane, his desire to see them stripped of all honors, and his own overwhelmingambition.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 October 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Moylan, James. L'Orient
    Arrival of Captain Thomas Bell with despatches for them. Captain McNeill's uneasiness over the presence of the prisoners on board his vessel.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Swaller, George. Dinan
    Account of his capture, first by the English and then by the French, and his present imprisonment at Dinan; begs that he may be sent home to serve his country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Stockton, Samuel W. Frankfort-on-the-Main
    A ship arrived at Bordeaux reports Rhode Island taken and the British troops made prisoners; hopes it is authentic. Rumors afloat that the Court of Spain has resolved to take an immediate and open part in favor of America. Reports in the English papers of the discontent in France against M. de Sartine and Franklin, who (they say) had to take refuge at Versailles from the resentment of the mob.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 October 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Langdon, John. Portsmouth. N.H
    Offering to furnish the navy of France with masts if any gentlemen there will take the contract; his terms.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 21; A.L.S. 1p.; de Pellizer Abbè. Paris
    At work on a Spanish, French and Latin dictionary; it has just occurred to him to add to these the English and so make the work useful to the United States; begs Franklin's interest and protection in this design.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Witel, Jérémie (S. Fauche's son-in-law). Paris
    Introducing himself as a member of the Sociètè Typographique de Lausanne, and begs for an interview.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 22; A.L.S. 4p.; Bache, Richard. Philadelphia
    Their removal into town a month before. News of Captain Frederick de Wernecke being alive and well. Mr. Lutterloh's answer to the Count de Wiltgerstein's demand. Will inquire into the Duchesse de Melfort's business in the Jersey's. Desires to know the value of certain types which he has sold to the State of Virginia. Congratulates him on his appointment as Minister Plenipotentiary; Pennsylvania the only state which voted against him; the openly expressed enmity of Lee and lzard; strong feeling expressed against his having his grandson as secretary, owing to his father's principles; exchange of Governor Franklin has been effected. Hopes the bearer of this will be the Marquis de Lafayette, who returns to his own country crowned with laurels. Reminds Franklin of a hint in a former letter of certain commercial advantages he promised to throw in his way.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 22; A.L.S. 1p.; ------, Borel. Paris
    Reminding Franklin of his promise to send him the coat of arms of the United States; impossible to finish his work without this mark of a brave and free nation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 22; A.L.S. 1p.; de Champigny, Col. Amsterdam
    Has received no answer to his two letters written two months before; begs Franklin not to forget the contract they entered into and to forward him the twelve ducats.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Kéralio-Luxembourg, Louis-Félix Guynement de.
    Begging for news from America on behalf of Madame la Comtesse de Deux-ponts, and to his brother le Chevalier de Keralio.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 October 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Hopkinson, Francis. Philadelphia